## **JUSTIN T. VAN DIJK**

**E** j.t.vandijk@ucl.ac.uk **in** linkedin.com/in/jtvandijk

**W** www.mappingdutchman.com **D** 0000-0001-5496-425X

#### **Profile**

Human geographer. Data scientist. Teacher. Interested in urban analytics, geo-demographics, urban transport, spatial inequalities, and big data applications in scarce data environments. Extensive experience in the domain of Geographic Information Systems, urban studies, and transport research. Possesses a wide skill set in the field of advanced spatial analysis, including experience with Python programming, R scripting, and PostgreSQL/PostGIS.

#### **Present appointments**

2020 - Present Associate Lecturer, University College London

Department of Geography. Associate Lecturer in Quantitative Social Science (0.4 FTE). Contributing to the M.Sc. modules *Principles of Spatial Analysis* and *Advanced Topics in Social and Geographic Data Science* as well as the undergraduate module *Introduction to Quantitative Research* 

Methods.

2018 - Present Postdoctoral Research Associate, University College London

Department of Geography. Research Associate in the Geospatial Analytics and Computing Research Group (0.6 FTE). Analysis and visualisation of big spatial population data sets with a strong focus on geo-demographics, internal migration, and inter-generational social mobility and spatial

inequalities.

## **Previous appointments**

2014 - 2017 **Junior Lecturer**, Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics. Part-time appointment.

2013 **Junior Lecturer**, Utrecht University

Department of Human Geography and Planning.

2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics.

2009 - 2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Utrecht University

Department of Human Geography and Planning.

#### **Education**

2014 - 2017 **Doctor of Philosophy**, Stellenbosch University

Transport Economics. Dissertation title: "Designing Travel Behaviour Change interventions: A spatiotemporal perspective".

2011 - 2013 Master of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0. Cum Laude.

Human Geography and Planning. Dissertation title: "Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa".

2007 - 2011 Bachelor of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0.

Human Geography and Planning. Dissertation title: "Contemporary Orientalism? Representations of Islam and Muslims in the Dutch Press: a content analysis of 'De Volkskrant' and 'De Telegraaf', 2001-2010".

## Refereed publications: International journals

2020 Van Dijk, J. T. and Longley, P. A. Interactive display of surname distributions in historic and contemporary Great Britain. Journal of Maps

16(1): 68-76. doi: <u>10.1080/17445647.2020.1746418</u>

Kandt, J., **Van Dijk, J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. Family name origins and intergenerational demographic change in Great Britain. *Annals of the American Association of Geographers*. 110(6): 1726-1742. doi:

10.1080/24694452.2020.1717328

Engin, Z., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lan, T., Longley, P. A., Treleaven, P., Batty, M., and Penn, A. Data-driven urban management: Mapping the landscape. *Journal of Urban Management* 9(2): 140-150. Publication. doi: 10.1016/j.jum.2019.12.001

**Van Dijk**, **J. T.** Identifying activity-travel points from GPS-data with multiple moving windows. *Computers, Environment and Urban Systems* 70: 84-101.

doi: 10.1016/j.compenv urbsys.2018.02.004

2017 Van Dijk, J. T. and Krygsman, S.C. Using GPS-based activity spaces and opportunity indicators for travel behaviour analysis. *Journal of Urban Technology* 25(2): 105-124. doi: 10.1080/10630732.2017.1400814

**Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and De Jong, T. Post-processing GPS tracks in reconstructing travelled routes in a GIS-environment: Network subset selection and attribute adjustment. *Annals of GIS* 23(3): 203-217. doi: 10.1080/19475683.2017.1340340

Idahosa, L. O. and **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** Freedom for whom in South Africa? Inequality, unemployment and the elderly. *Development* 58(1): 96-102. doi: 10.1057/dev.2015.18

# 2015

2018

**Van Dijk, J. T.**, Krygsman, S. C., and De Jong, T. Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa. *Journal of Transport and Land use* 8(3): 95-114. doi: 10.5198/jtlu.2015.555

## Refereed publications: Under consideration

2021

**Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., Using linked consumer registers to estimate internal migration in the United Kingdom. *Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series A (Statistics in Society)*. Under review following a first round of reviewer's comments.

Lan, T., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A., Cities as platforms for social mobility in Great Britain, 1881-1901. *Urban Studies*. Under review following a first round of reviewer's comments.

## **Refereed publications: Book chapters**

2021

**Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., Using linked consumer and administrative data to model demographic changes in London's city fringe. In: Clarke, G., Birkin, M., and Stimson, B. (Eds.), *Applications of Big Data in geography and planning*. Cheltenham: Edward Elgar Publishing Ltd. In press.

2013

Wolfensberger M., Dekker, M., Van Dijk, J. T., Zubizarreta, J., Hait, C., Mann, C., and Lucas, C. Learning as salon: Honors International Collaboration. In: Mulvaney, M. K. and Klein, K. (Eds.), *Preparing Tomorrow's Global Leaders: Honors International Education*, pp. 75-84. Lincoln: National Collegiate Honors Council. NCHC Monograph Series.

## **Refereed publications: Conference proceedings**

2021

**Van Dijk, J. T.** and Longley, P. A. Developing a data infrastructure for bespoke demographic analysis. *Proceedings of the 29th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Cardiff: Cardiff University. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.4664749

Chen, M., Chi, B., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. The use of Linked Consumer Registers to understand social mobility and residential mobility. *Proceedings of the 29th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Cardiff: Cardiff University. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.4665856

Kuleszo, J., Coulter, R., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. Linking consumer datasets to chart residential moves in private rental housing in England and Wales. *Proceedings of the 29th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Cardiff: Cardiff University. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.4665818

2020 Van Dijk, J. T. and Longley, P. A. Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names. In: Westerholt, R. and Mocnick, F.-B. (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science (PLATIAL'19)*.

Warwick: Warwick University. 23-31. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.3628863

Van Dijk, J. T., Lansley, G., Lan, T., and Longley, P. A. Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.

Lan, T., Lansley, G., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A. Geocoding historical census records in England and Wales. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.

Van Dijk, J. T. and Krygsman, S. C. Mobile technologies for data collection in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of mobility research. #CelebrateGeography: Proceedings of the 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers (SSAG 2016). Stellenbosch: SunMedia. 180-189.

Van Dijk, J. T. and Krygsman, S. C. Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study. *Proceedings of the 34th Southern African Transport Conference (SATC 2015). Pretoria: Southern Africa Transport Conference*. 448-460.

## **Professional publications**

Van Dijk, J. T. and De Jong, T. Medische voorzieningen in kaart.
Bereikbaarheid medische voorzieningen in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng en Sekhukhune [Accessibility of Medical services in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng and Sekhukhune]. Geografie 19 (5): 18-20.

#### **Authored books**

2017 Van Dijk, J. T. Designing Travel Behaviour Change Interventions: a spatiotemporal perspective [dissertation]. Stellenbosch: Stellenbosch University. Persistent URL: <a href="https://doi.org/10.17/102809">https://doi.org/10.17/102809</a>

#### **Research and travel grants**

2021	Co-funded and Collaborative ESRC Ph.D. Studentship, UBEL DTP £ 57,761 / 3 years (co-l, with P. A. Longley)
2020	Frank Carter Travel Fund, University College London £ 550
2016	Postgraduate travel grant, National Research Foundation South Africa <b>ZAR 24,222</b>

2015 NRF-DST innovation scholarship, National Research Foundation and

Department of Science and Technology South Africa

ZAR 330,000 / 3 years

Stellenbosch merit bursary, Stellenbosch University

ZAR 50,000 / 2 years

2014 Scholarship award for full-time doctoral studies, Stellenbosch University

ZAR 390,000 / 3 years

#### **Created research datasets**

2021 Migration Model, 1997 – 2016

The Migration Model is a dataset that ascribes records pertaining to individuals that vacate a property to their most probable destination address, using a UK-wide population data set: the Linked Consumer Registers. The dataset comprises circa 42 million records. The 1997 – 2020 upgrade will be available later this year. Access to this dataset can be secured through the Consumer Data Research Centre (data.cdrc.ac.uk).

2021 Linked Consumer Registers, 1997 – 2020

The Linked Consumer Registers are a dataset that contain the names and addresses for adults in the UK in annual snapshots from 1997 onwards to 2020. They are compiled from reported outputs from linking public versions of the electoral roll and consumer registers (supplied by value-added resellers). The dataset comprises circa 141 million records. Access to this dataset can be secured through the Consumer Data Research Centre (data.cdrc.ac.uk).

## **Teaching experience**

2020 - Present Lecturing, University College London

- GEOG0114: Principles of Spatial Analysis (M.Sc.). Module page: <u>itvandijk.github.io/GEOG0114/</u>

- GEOG0125: Advanced Topics in Social and Geographic Data Science (M.Sc.). Module page: <a href="mailto:itotalcolor: itvandiik.github.io/GEOG0125/">itvandiik.github.io/GEOG0125/</a>
- Principal dissertation supervisor of two M.Sc. students

## 2019 - Present High-school Student Supervision, Nuffield Foundation

Supervision of first-generation prospective university students as part of the annual Nuffield Future Researchers widening participation programme.

2019 Seminar Speaker, University College London

Co-organiser and speaker in the "Technical Tuesdays" Seminar Series on methods and techniques for quantitative researchers. Module material: github.com/itvandiik/TechnicalTuesdays

2014 - 2017 **Lecturing**, Stellenbosch University

- Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis (B.Sc. Hons, M.Sc.)
- Secondary dissertation supervisor of two B.Sc. Hons students

*2013* **Lecturing**, Utrecht University

- Introduction to Human Geography and Planning (B.Sc.)
- Research Methods and Techniques (B.Sc.)
- Introduction to Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc.)
- Advanced Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc., M.Sc.)
- Principal dissertation supervisor of three B.Sc. students

2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Stellenbosch University

- Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis (B.Sc. Hons, M.Sc.)

2009 - 2012 **Teaching Assistant**, Utrecht University

- Introduction to Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc.)
- Advanced Geographic Information Systems (B.Sc., M.Sc.)
- Transport Geography (B.Sc.)
- Honours College Geosciences (B.Sc.)

## Ph.D. supervision

2021 **Secondary Supervisor**, University College London

Shunya Kimura on the topic of "Geographies of harmful gambling behaviour and their remediation". Project will commence September 2021.

#### Ph.D. examination

2020 **Ph.D. upgrade**, University College London

Jakub Wyszomierski on the topic of "Hybrid geodemographics and creation of the 2021 Output Area Classification"

#### **Guest lectures and invited research seminars**

2020 "Applied Geoinformatics: Insights into human mobility patterns". Guest

lecture Department of Physical Planning [online]. School of Architecture and

Planning New Delhi, India, October 29, 2020.

2019 "What's in a name? Storing surname geographies for both visualisation and

analysis". Guest lecture Graduate School Economic and Management

Sciences. Stellenbosch University, South Africa, March 8, 2019.

2018	"What's in a name? Storing surname geographies for both visualisation and analysis". Research seminar Geo+Data London (AGI/CDRC event). <i>University College London, United Kingdom, December 4, 2018.</i>
2017	"Using GPS-enabled smartphones for Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change interventions". Guest lecture Utrecht University Summer School on "GPS data analysis". <i>Utrecht University, the Netherlands, July 12, 2017.</i>
2016	"GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the module "Introduction to GIS". <i>Utrecht University, the Netherlands, February 18, 2016.</i>
2015	"GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the module "Introduction to GIS". <i>Utrecht University, the Netherlands, November 25, 2015.</i>
	ed at international conferences
2021	"Developing a data infrastructure for bespoke demographic analysis" 29th

2021	"Developing a data infrastructure for bespoke demographic analysis". 29th
	Conference of GIS Research UK. Cardiff, United Kingdom, September 14 –
	September 16, 2021.

- 2019 "Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names". 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science. *Coventry, United Kingdom, September 5 September 6, 2019.* 
  - "Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change". 27th Conference of GIS Research UK. *Newcastle, United Kingdom, April 23 April 26, 2019.*
- 2016 "Mobile data collection techniques in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of transport research". 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers. Stellenbosch, South Africa, September 25 September 25, 2016.
  - "Designing a Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change Intervention: Smartphones and Space-Time Accessibility Analysis". Mobile Tartu 2016. Tartu, Estonia, June 29 – July 1, 2016.
- 2015 "Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study". 34th Southern African Transport Conference. *Pretoria, South Africa, 6 July July 9, 2015.*
- 2014 "Twenty years of Freedom: The role of the Old Persons Grant in addressing unemployment and inequality in a young democracy". 12th Development Dialogue "Rethinking Democracy". The Hague, the Netherlands, October 16 October 17, 2014.

"Towards spatial justice: The spatial Equity Effects of a Toll Road in Cape Town, South Africa". World Symposium on Transport and Land Use. *Delft, the Netherlands, June 24 – June 27, 2014.* 

## **Community service**

2020 - Present Under One Sky

Volunteering. Provision of food and assistance to the homeless community

living on the streets of London.

2014 - 2015 Social Sciences for Development conference

Member of the local organising committee at Stellenbosch University for

the 2015 Social Sciences for Development conference.

## Web development

2019 - Present Gamble Aware

Data analysis, web mapping, and visualisation of the geographical distribution of supply and demand for treatment and support for

problematic gamblers. Maps are available through:

www.begambleaware.org/mapping-problem-gambling-severity

2018 - Present GBNames

GBNames explores the spread of family names across Great Britain, using historic censuses and recent consumer registers, and links surnames to

consumer data statistics. Website available through:

apps.cdrc.ac.uk/gbnames/

## **External projects**

2021 - Present World Bank

Generation of travel time indicators and market access indicators for small administrative units in Ethiopia. This project is part of a wider study conducted by the World Bank that aims to identify and tackle deeply rooted binding constraints that could hamper the gains of economic growth being spread evenly across regions and between rural and urban

areas.

2020 UBEL DTP

Scoping study, consisting of both desk research and in-person interviews, to identify potential factors and themes that underpin successful partnerships

and collaborations between academia and industry.

2019 Greater London Authority

Preparation of selected data products on ethnicity, population churn,

migration, and social mobility for the Greater London Authority.

2016 – 2017 Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator

Data analysis using well-known statistical techniques as well as more advanced machine learning classifiers for Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator to better understand, and possibly predict, successful job

placements.

2009 AfriScope

Contributions to a study on the accessibility of government services in the Integrated Sustainable Rural Development (ISRD) Nodes in South Africa.

**Review** 

2021 Transactions in GIS

2020 Computers, Environment, and Urban Systems

Journal of Transport Geography

Transactions in GIS

2019 Transactions in GIS

Journal of Transport Geography

The Israel Science Foundation (Grant review)

Journal of Traffic and Transportation Engineering

2018 Journal of Transport Geography

Computers, Environment, and Urban Systems

2016 Area Development and Policy2015 Journal of Transport and Land Use

### **Core technical skills**

Geographic Information Systems R, Python, Q-GIS, ArcGIS

Data processing R, Python, Unix shell, GNU Parallel

Data analysisR, PythonData visualisationggplot2Project managementGit, GitHubWeb mappingLeaflet.js

Web development HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Django

Database management PostgreSQL, PostGIS

Typesetting LaTeX, markdown, rmarkdown, bookdown

## Language proficiency

Dutch Native proficiency

English Full professional proficiency isiXhosa Basic conversational proficiency

## References

Professor Paul Longley

Professor of Geographic Information Science, University College London

E p.longley@ucl.ac.uk

T +44 20 7679 0500

Dr Neil Rankin

Extraordinary Associate Professor Economics, Stellenbosch University; Data Scientist, Predictive Insights

**E** neil@predictiveinsights.net **T** +27 83 296 0907

Dr Joanna Wilkin

Lecturer Social and Geographic Data Science, University College London

**E** j.wilkin@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 20 7678 0500